Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 2 -- Letters to Franklin 1777 January-1778 March Mss.B.F85inventory02
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 16; N.S. 1p.; Melmoth, Courtney. Paris
    Card of introduction.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778. March] 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Brillon, Mme d'Hardancourt. Passy
    Declines to engage in a discussion with Franklin on the Ten Commandments. Points out the reserve and discretion in conduct which women are obliged to observe and the liberty allowed to men in their relations with the opposite sex.
    Postscript about a collection of Scotch airs received from Mr. Alexander.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Dec., 1906, 311.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 16; A.N.S. 1p.; Melmoth, Courtney. Paris
    Introducing a gentleman who wishes to see Franklin about a discovery relating to powder and saltpetre.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Clough, Elizabeth. London
    Enclosed letter for her only son in America.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 March 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Walke, Jno. Bordeaux
    Announcing the conclusion of the dispute between Mr. Bond and himself; verdict of the court gives him leave to depart from Bordeaux with his vessel; each party to pay their own costs; advisability of carrying on the suit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 17; A.L.S. John Houstoun. 2p.; The Governor of Georgia. Savannah
    The son of a Georgian, Mr. O'Brien, who was sent to school at Smith's Academy near London, the report prevails that he has been trepanned on board a British man-of-war in the Thames and detained as a prisoner; begs Franklin to inquire into this matter and if it is true, effect exchange of prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Bridgen, Edward
    Introducing M. Garnier, Secretary to the French Embassy, who desires the honor of being known to the greatest man living.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Recommending Captain Dunn and Mr. Curtis, lately arrived from Georgia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778.] March 19; A.L.S.; Melmoth, Courtney. Paris
    Sending the promised pamphlet on American affairs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Gébelin, Antoine Court de. Paris
    Enclosing a letter from Mr. Hutton. Disappointed at not meeting him at the house of the Marquis of Mirabeau. Will send him the 5th volume of the "Monde Primitif" for which he subscribed.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 March 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, William. Chaillot
    Asking for a copy of the treaties they have entered into with the Court of France, that he may not propose anything inconsistent therewith to the Courts of Vienna and Berlin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 19; L.S. 4p.; Poop, Jonathan. Paris
    With reference to a fatal quarrel between a civilian and some officers and to a court trial resulting thereform.
    (In French and English.)
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 March 20; A.L. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Congratulating them on the union of America and France; the reception of the news and the rumors afloat. Quotes his own letter to the Grand Factor. Offer of protection for himself just received.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Roches de Condormes, —. St. Nicolas-de-la-Grave
    Concerning a work of his, which sets forth an admirable method of learning the French language.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Montaudoüin de la Touche, Jean-Gabriel. Nantes
    Delighted at the commercial treaty between America and France. Has a Medallion of Franklin in terra cotta, very well executed; quotes the latin motto to be inscribed thereon. Sends messages to various friends. Expresses, for Franklin, the greatest admiration and affection. A commercial proposition of one of his friends, which he desires Franklin to communicate to Mr. William Lee.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 March 21; 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Matters concerning the Duchesse de Grammont. The Dolphin's seizure and the sentence of the Admiralty on it; encloses Tonnay's account.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 22; A.L.S. 1p.; MacMahon, John. At the Military school in Paris
    Congratulating him on the results of the negotiations with France; thinks America's independence is assured—when will poor Ireland's turn come? Concerning a fine poem inscribed to Franklin by a lawyer of Avignon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Raudière, J. D. R. de
    Has written Franklin a poem entitled "The Ameriquiade" which he sends with other papers; promises never to offend in this manner again.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 March 22; Verscs. 1p.; Raudière, J.-D. Ramier de
    Addressing his poem "The Ameriquiade" to Franklin, Deane and Lee. Hope they will do something to alleviate his distress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 23; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lee, William. Chaillot
    Will wait on Franklin the next day to take leave of him and hopes the copy of the treaties will be ready for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 23; L. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel. London.
    Several of his friends disposed to lend money to the United States; desired by one of them to find out the manner in which the loans are made and the amount of interest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Congratulating him on the glorious conclusion of the treaty with France. His devotion to the cause of America. All the English ships in the harbor have been stopped by order of the Court; the captains of the French vessels fearing a retaliation, dare not proceed to sea. Recommends Captain Chandler as an able pilot.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 23; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bertier, Père Joseph Etienne. l'Oratoire
    Expressing the greatest interest on the part of himself and his confrères in Franklin's success; trusts that the affair which Franklin has charge of will come to a successful issue.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Hore, F Dilkes. St. Omer
    A declaration of war on the part of Great Britain makes it necessary for him to apply to Franklin for permission to remain at St. Omer with his family; has endeavored for many months to get to Boston but without success; has offered his services, through General Gates, to the Congress. Has written Franklin many letters under a disguised name; Colonel Mercer will inform Franklin who he is.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Adams, John. Brest
    His advice to Captain Landais was to apply to the Intendant of Marine for such materials and workmen as were needed to repair the ship; disposition to be made of the prisoners. Applies to Franklin for clothes on behalf of the midshipmen and other petty officers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Rumors of war between England and France. Foreign news; war decided upon between Turkey and Russia. Amusing dialogue between the French Ambassador, M. de Bérenger, and Sir Joseph Yorke. Is longer laughed at foor his chimerical views, but is spied upon worse than ever.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Nicephore, P
    Is a Capuchin monk, therefore cannot aid the Americans in the capacity of a soldier but is extremely anxious to go over as chaplain to the regiment in which two of his brothers serve; with some difficulty has obtained permission from his Superior; begs Franklin to intercede with M. de Sartine in his behalf.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Gruffy, — de. Paris
    As he has decided to live in America, begs Franklin's permission to call on him as compatriot; has a letter for him from the Comtesse de Conway.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778. March]? 25th; A.L.S. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Cannot give Franklin a list of his sins, as it would be too long; they all spring from one source, however, Cannot approve or tolerate the dangerous principle, which Franklin seems to have adopted; that love and friendship can be divided up ad infinitum and distributed amongst any number of persons.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Du Mont, -----
    Reminding Franklin of his promise to aid him in his design of continuing his History of the English Colonies in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 25; L. 1p.; Genet, Edme Jacques, d.1781
    Concerning the manufacture and purchase of various cannon. Proposition of M. Hannet to establish an iron foundry in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1778 March 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Hennet, ----. Paris
    Very anxious to know when he may pay his respects to Franklin and talk with him on certain matters of importance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Gastellier, René-Georges. Montargis
    Overjoyed at Franklin's triumph over his enemies; congratulates him on the intrepidity with which he has upheld the cause of liberty.
  - to Messrs. Franklin and Deane., 1778 March 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Merckle, Joh Ph. Amsterdam
    Forms with his friends a considerable expedition, which is almost ready to sail. The person from whom he purchased arms, conformable to the Commissioners' list, insists upon his taking them on board; impossible to place such an article in the cargo; begs them to interfere.
    A. E dated April 13, by Franklin. The Commissioners have done everything incumbent on them relative to Mr. Mcrckle's affairs, and do not incline to have any further concern with them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1778 March 26; A.L.S. 2p.; de Laval, -----. Paris
    Desires to ask Franklin's advice on certain matters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1778 March 26; Mem. 2p.; Montécot, -----. Paris
    M. Baillot has invented a new metal of a whitish gray color suitable for coins of small denomination. Offers to disclose his secret and to send a sample of the metal made by him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1778 March 27; L. and Diss. S. 11p.; Desgianiéres, -----. Chaillot
    Sending Franklin an article on the love of liberty, and proposing a system of revenue for the United States instead of the ruinous and un-just taxation in force in most countries.
  - to The American Commissioners, 1778 March 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Arrival of their good friend, the Factor. Awaits only an important letter from them before setting out for Amsterdam; explains the several preliminary steps before the proper moment arrives for Franklin to appear on the scene; impossible to push affairs further without important instructions from them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 27; A.L.S 2p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis-Alexandre, duc de La Roche-Guyon et de.
    At last America and France are declared friends, and Franklin, Minister Plenipotentiary. Anxious to know if Mr. Deane is really returning to America; desires to see him before he sails. Expects to dine with Captain Jones in a day or two on board one of the French frigates. Begs for news.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Decided that, owing to his connection with the Spanish Court, he could not venture as far as Germany; his brother has therefore set out. Concerning the business of the loan bills.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Johnstone, John. St. Malo
    Narrating a series of misfortunes befallen him since he sailed from Dartmouth on the 27th of June. Is now at St. Malo, in France; begs Franklin to obtain his freedom that he may return to his native country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 28; L.S. 2p.; de Basmarin et Raimbaux, Recules. Bordeaux
    The close bonds between France and America. The admiration due to Franklin's talents and the homage due his character.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 28; L.S. 3p.; La Plaigne, Emmanuel-Pierre de. Bordeaux
    Difficulties and discussions he has had with Messrs. Bayard and Co. on the score of passengers; fears that they will not keep to their agreement. Expects to leave for I'Isle de Réthe following Monday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Ross, John. Nantes
    Introducing Mr. John B. Paschen, a native of Hamburg, who desires the honor of meeting the first Ambassador of the United States of America; assistance he has received from Mr. Paschen in his claim against the city of Hamburg.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Du Mont, ------. Paris
    Thanking Franklin for the information he has given him; if he continues his "History of the English Colonies," will make use of it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Izard, Ralph. Paris
    Concerning the desirability of granting, to a certain man, a passport to Italy. Disappointed at receiving no explanation on certain points mentioned in his letter of January 30th, wherein he thought himself injured. Desires to know if he is to expect any answer from the Commissioners to his letter of the 5th inst.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 29; A.L.S. 7p.; Wyss, ------. Longwy
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 29; A.L.S. 4p.; de la Genetière. -----. Paris
    A long account of misfortunes. To Franklin alone could he confide his sorrow without shame, and beg for assistance.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Acknowledging his appointment as commercial agent for the Secret Committee of Congress at the ports of Bayonne, Bordeaux, Rochefort and La Rochelle; will observe all orders implicitly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Capture by the frigate Oiseau of a privateer brig of sixteen guns belonging to London. Arrival of the ship Harmony Hall, loaded with tobacco, rice, slaves, etc., from Newbern, North Carolina.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Lambert, ------. Paris
    Hopes Franklin will find in the enclosed letter enough to justify his troubling him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 30; L. 4p.; Lambert, ------
    Copy of a letter sent to M. Sabbathier, Secretary of the Academy of Chalons, on the suppression of mendicancy together with his answer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Rochemure, —, abbé de. Paris
    Begs for the honor of a moment's audience.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Goudar, -----. Aubenas
    Begs Franklin to procure him an engraving of General Washington.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Izard, Ralph. Paris
    Considers that he has acted justifiably.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 Dec. 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jno. Nantes
    His nephew (Jonathan's) departure for Bordeaux. Sends the public papers. Gives extract from a letter (1 p.) concerning the probable destination of the English fleet, which left New york on October 19th.
  - Messrs. Franklin and Deane, 1778 March 31; L.S. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    The report of Mr. Deane's intending departure from Paris obliges him to repeat the request that the public accounts should be settled; reasons for this demand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 31; A.L.S. 2p.; O'Gorman, Thomas, chevalier
    Concerning the wines he sent Franklin; reason for their dearness; desires the account settled as soon as possible.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 March 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Cargo of the Duchesse de Grammont; certain claims made by one of the workmen; attitude of their cheif, M. Merchier. [Dr. of answer on back of L. in handwriting of Arthur Lee.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Hodge, William. Cadiz
    Account of his cruize since leaving Bilboa; number of prizes captured; chased by two English frigates; final arrival at Cadiz; desires advice and orders.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 March] Sunday.; A.L.S. 2p.; Melmoth, Courtney. Paris
    Reason why the salt-petre man failed to keep his engagement. Question of his obtaining the promised small appointment from Mr. Deane of Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 March]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; dechamolle
    Went to America in 1777 with a troop of Chasseurs; captured by the English and imprisoned at St. Augustine in Florida; cruel treatment; request for his release or exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March; Poem. 7p.; -----, -----
    Ode to King Louis XVI entitled "The Awakening of France."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March; A.L.S. 3p.; Lovell, Patience [Wright]
    Relations between England and America. Political information.
  - to W.T. Franklin, 1777 August 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Sends a packet for his grandfather; bids him goodbye; asks to be remembered to Mr. [Silas] Deane, who must appoint a day to see his cannon at the arsenal. (in French)